A Register of the Nadia L. Shapiro Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Nadia L. Shapiro papers
1910-1984
90004
Shapiro, Nadia L. (Nadia Lavrova), 1897-1989.
12 manuscript boxes, 2 phonorecords (5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Papers of the Russian-American writer and journalist include writings, letters, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the Russian Civil War in Siberia, and to Russian émigré life in China and the United States. Contains a memoir of the Russian Civil War in the Blagoveshchensk area and of the trial of the Socialist Revolutionary A. N. Alekseevskii in Blagoveshchensk in 1918 (with a translation by Elena Varneck). Also includes records of N. L. Shapiro's work with the Office of War Information during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biography Note
1897 October 20 Born, Irkutsk, Siberia, Russia
1914 May High school diploma, Irkutsk, Siberia, Russia
1915-1916 Elementary school teacher certificate, one-year pedagogical course in Blagoveschensk, Siberia, Russia
1916-1917 Studied at the Moscow Women's College, Russia
1917-1918 Teacher of English language, Blagoveschensk Polytechnical School, Siberia, Russia
1918 Fled with her family from the Bolsheviks to Harbin, Manchuria, China
1918-1920 Interpreter and feature writer for the newspaper Novosti zhizni, Harbin, Manchuria, China
1920-1921 Performed literary work and studied Japanese, Yokohama, Japan
1921 Foreign Editor, Zaria newspaper, Harbin, Manchuria, China
1922 August Arrived in the United States under the sponsorship of the Harbin Y.M.C.A.
1923 May 29 B.A., University of California, Berkeley (after Russian diplomas were validated)
1923-1932 Feature writer and Book and Art page editor for the San Francisco Examiner
1928 February 6 Acquired U.S. citizenship
1932-1942 Free-lanced, contributing to the Christian Science Monitor and various West Coast publications, under byline "Nadia Lavrova"
1936-1937 Play reader and research writer/editor for the Federal Theatre in San Francisco, Work Projects Administration
1937-1942 Legal research editor, Historical Records Survey of Northern California, Work Projects Administration
1942-1945 Translator and examiner, U.S. Office of Censorship
1945 Writer, U.S. Office of War Information
1945 May-June Member, Russian section, Interpreters and Translators Bureau of the International Secretariat at the United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco
1946-1953 Foreign broadcast monitor, U.S. Central Intelligence Agency
1989 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Nadia Shapiro papers consist of material related to the life and work of the Russian-American writer and journalist Nadezhda Lazarevna Shapiro.
The collection includes correspondence, writings, pamphlets, clippings, stories, essays, sketches, other printed matter, photographs, and other pictorial materials relating to the Russian Civil War in Siberia, and to Russian émigré life in China and the United States. There is also material relating to her U.S. government service during World War II.
Nadia Shapiro was a freelance writer, and also worked as a staff feature writer for the San Francisco Examiner, San Francisco Chronicle, Los Angeles Times (Sunday Magazine), Christian Science Monitor, and Russian language publications in the United States. Most of her writing in English was done under the pen name of "Nadia Lavrova" or "NL," while in Russian she signed her works as "Nadezhda Lavrova."
Nadia Shapiro devoted a major part of her spare time to literary activities without, however, submitting anything for publication, which she justified as due to the peculiar nature of her confidential work with different federal agencies. She gathered a great variety of notes and drafts of sketches, stories, essays, and book and chapter outlines –- all in preparation for the later processing of some of this material into stories and books.
The collection includes a wealth of romantic short stories. A few of them were published during Shapiro's freelancing and news writing days. Considering her Russian origin, there are also notes for an autobiographical narrative "My Old Home Town Was Blagoveschensk," which covers the Russian Civil War and the trial of the Socialist Revolutionary A. N. Alekseevskii in 1918.
The Hoover Institution Archives acquired the Nadia Shapiro papers in 1990.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into eight series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Writings, Subject File, Printed Matter, Art Work, Postcards, and Photographs.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
Alekseevskii, Aleksandr Nikolaevich.; Partiia sotsialistov-revoliutsionerov.; United States. Office of War Information.; Russians--China.; Russians--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; Blagoveshchensk (Amurskaia oblast, Russia); Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Phonorecords.; Journalists.; Varneck, Elena, 1891-1976.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1910-1975. (Box 1)
  Autobiographical material, business cards, certificates and diplomas, correspondence with family, curricula vitae, employment records, evaluations and acknowledgements, invitations, letters of recommendation, records of United States government service, statement of assets and will, and telegram, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Autobiographical material, 1928-1958 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Business cards, n.d. (Folder 1: 2)
  - Certificates, diplomas, and transcripts, 1910-1975 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Correspondence (family)
    - Shapiro, Fanny Grigorievna (mother), 1945-1956 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Shapiro, H. (cousin), 1938 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Shapiro, Lazar Solomonovich (father), 1924-1933. (Folder 1: 6)
      Includes articles on his trial in Harbin and obituary
    - Shapiro, Mary (sister), 1924-1971. (Folder 1: 7)
      Includes appeals from Nadia and her mother to various international institutions concerning Mary
  - Curricula vitae, 1932-1952 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Employment records, 1942-1973 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Evaluations and acknowledgements, 1944-1953 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Invitations, n.d. (Folder 1: 11)
  - Letters of recommendation, 1922-1946 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Records of United States government service
    - United States. Central Intelligence Agency, 1946-1953 (Folder 1: 13)
    - United States. Civil Service Commission, 1942-1943 (Folder 1: 14)
    - United States. Foreign Broadcast Information Service, 1943-1948 (Folder 1: 15)
    - United States. Office of Censorship, 1942-1945 (Folder 1: 16)
    - United States. Office of War Information, 1945 (Folder 1: 17-18)
    - United States. State Department
      - General. Request for application form in order to recover money on old Russian government loans, savings account books and paper money bills in case of settlement with Soviet government, 1934 (Folder 1: 19)
      - Bureau of International Information and Cultural Affairs, 1944-1946 (Folder 1: 20)
    - United States. War Department. Civilian Personnel Division, 1941-1946 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Statement of assets and will, 1974, 1981 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Telegram regarding interview for the position as United Nations representative, 1946 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 24)
- Correspondence, 1914-1974. (Box 2)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Unidentified, 1914-1975 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Alameda Free Library, Alameda, California.
    See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - Alsimoto, S., 1921 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Anderson, Grace K., 1969 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Andrews, Clarence L., 1936-1940.
  - Balakshin, Peter, 1953, 1967 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Bank of Manchuria, Harbin, 1922 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Blagoveshchenskoe utro, 1915 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Borzov, N., 1941 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Burkhardt, Charlotte, 1955 (Folder 2: 8)
  - California Historical Society, San Francisco, California, 1971.
  - Chamberlin, Sonya and William Henry, 1934-1945 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Christian Science Monitor (Pacific News Bureau), 1933 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Clarke, Edward (San Francisco Examiner), 1926 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Delaplane, Stanton, 1958 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Detective Tales (Edwin Baird), 1923 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Dixon, Constance, 1931-1933. (Folder 2: 14)
    See also Photographs/Constance Dixon
  - Dolgopolov, Alexander, 1972-1974. (Folder 2: 15)
    Includes his articles
  - Driser, Mrs., n.d. (Folder 2: 16)
  - Fujihisa(?), G., 1920 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Gaimusho, Tokyo, 1921 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Golitzen, L., Princess, 1925 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Gordenker, Olga Vladimirovna, 1929-1932 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Gris, Henry, n.d. (Folder 2: 21)
  - Gusev-Orenburgskii, S. I., 1950 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Haley, George, 1927 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Helm, Jean, 1923-1957.; See also Photographs/Jean Paine (Spray) Helm (Folder 2: 24-25)
  - Herhmeister(?), H., 1921 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1928 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Hubbart, Bernard R., n.d. (Folder 3: 3)
  - John Howell ߝ Books, 1971.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - Johnson, Mary Dibrell, 1970-1971 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Jury, John Clare, 1973 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Kamakura, Machi, 1920 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Kashevarof, A. P., 1936.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - Kavanshin, K., 1921 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Kawanishi, K., 1921 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Kawasaki, Torao, 1925, 1927 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Keilien, Julia, 1920 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Kourennoff, Pavel Matveevich, 1944.; See Subject File/ Kourennoff, Pavel Matveevich
  - Kraatz, Charles A., 1957 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Lawrence, Millicent, 1954 (Folder 3: 12)
  - LeBaron, Gaye, 1968 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Lingel, Robert, 1938.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - London, Charmian, 1932 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Lopatin, Ivan, 1933 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Mack, W. H., 1935-1936 (Folder 3: 16)
  - Martin, Lawrence, 1939.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - Matsubara, D., 1920-1921 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Mattson, A., 1924 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Medy, N. P., 1946 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Miller, Edward M., 1934.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - Milo, Basil, 1929 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Nabokoff, Ekaterina S., 1960 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Nazarek, Kitt, 1974 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Nelson, Eric, 1946-1967 (Folder 3: 23)
  - New York Public Library, Acquisition Division, 1938.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - Newbern, L. R., 1933 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Novinka, Wholesalers and retailers of Russian books, Russian art, etc., 1934.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - Oldenbarnevelet, Zhanna, n.d. (Folder 3: 25)
  - Oshima, T., 1921 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Popular Fiction Publishing Company, 1924-1926 (Folder 3: 27)
  - Pushkarev, S., 1958 (Folder 3: 28)
  - Putnam, George Palmer, 1940-1941 (Folder 3: 29)
  - Reeve, Lloyd Eric, 1959 (Folder 3: 30)
  - Riemer, H. G., 1924 (Folder 3: 31)
  - Rokkaku, K., 1922 (Folder 3: 32)
  - Ross, Florence, 1962 (Folder 3: 33)
  - San Francisco Committee for Service to Emigrés, 1947 (Folder 3: 34)
  - Saxton, E. F., 1941 (Folder 3: 35)
  - Scott, Leona O., 1921 (Folder 3: 36)
  - Shulkevich, B. A., 1961 (Folder 3: 37)
  - Sinitsina, Gutya, n.d. (Folder 3: 38)
  - Soviet Union. Narodnyi komissariat po inostrannym delam (People's Commissariat for Foreign Affairs), 1928 (Folder 3: 39)
  - Sprindler family, 1933 (Folder 3: 40)
  - Stockley, Grey, n.d. (Folder 3: 41)
  - Taylor, H. H., 1928 (Folder 3: 42)
  - Tolentino, Gaudencio, 1923, 1926 (Folder 3: 43)
  - United States. Central Intelligence Agency, 1948 (Folder 3: 44)
  - United States. Library of Congress, 1930.; See Subject File/Honcharenko, Agapius
  - United States. Library of Congress, Division of Maps, 1939.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - United States. State Department, OIC, International Broadcasting Division, 1946 (Folder 3: 45)
  - University of California Chronicle, University of California, Berkeley, 1929-1931.; See Subject File/Honcharenko, Agapius
  - Velikoselsky, Vladimir, 1974. (Folder 3: 46)
    Includes scenario for a ballet in three acts, "Clara Milich"
  - Vinokuroff, Michael Z., 1929, 1934. (Folder 3: 47)
    Includes essay on history of Alaskan church
  - Vol'naia Sibir', Prague, 1929 (Folder 3: 48)
  - Willoughby, Barrett, 1927-1959.; See also Writings/"Old Sitka Saved" (Folder 3: 49-50)
  - Writer's Digest (Ada Masini), 1935-1936 (Folder 3: 51)
  - Young Women's Christian Association of China, National Committee, 1921 (Folder 3: 52)
  - Zaria, Harbin, 1922 (Folder 3: 53)
- Writings, 1913-1973. (Box 4)
  Articles, drafts, essays, sketches relating mostly to Russian history and culture in general and Alaska history and culture in particular, arranged chronologically by title
  - General
    - Untitled, undated (Folder 4: 1)
    - Notebooks of famous sayings, notes, short stories, verses, n.d. (Folder 4: 2)
      Holograph
    - Notes, 1920-1971. (Folder 4: 3)
      Holographs and typescripts
    - Poetry, translated from Russian, n.d. (Folder 4: 4)
      Typescript
    - Scrapbook of articles published in newspapers Blagoveschenskoe utro, Amurskoe ekho, Novosti zhizni, Delo Rossii, Zaria, Russkii golos, 1915-1924 (Folder 4: 5)
    - Suggestions for revised short stories, n.d. (Folder 4: 6)
  - Agapius Honcharenko,", n.d.; See Subject File/Honcharenko, Agapius
    Typescript.
  - "Alekseevskii, Aleksandr Nikolaevich,", See Subject File/Alekseevskii, Aleksandr Nikolaevich
    Holograph in Russian and typescript in English and Russian.
  - "The Americans...,", n.d.; See Subject File/Refugees ߝ Russian
  - "The Course of Revolutionary Events at Blagoveschensk" [in 1918], Siberia, n.d. (Folder 4: 7)
    Typescript. In Russian and English
  - Essay submitted to the Home Forum, n.d. (Folder 4: 8)
  - "Die Gattin eines russische [sic] Obersten sucht Garten...,", n.d. (Folder 4: 9)
  - Direct mail advertisement for G. L. Najarian oriental rug gallery, n.d. (Folder 4: 10)
  - "Freeman," play, n.d. (Folder 4: 11)
  - "Get That Picture,", n.d. (Folder 4: 12)
  - "He Who Rules Last," play, n.d. (Folder 4: 13)
  - "How I Came to Write in English,", n.d. (Folder 4: 14)
  - "Ideas for Possible Use in Fiction,", n.d. (Folder 4: 15)
  - "Khronika sobytii v gorode Blagoveschenske-na-Amure,", n.d. (Folder 4: 16)
  - "Lover, Don't Come Back,", n.d. (Folder 4: 17)
  - "Make up at Midnight,", n.d. (Folder 4: 18)
  - Memorandum on the five pictures of Japanese documents, See Subject File/Japan ߝ Secret service
  - "Nepravednyi sud,", n.d. (Folder 4: 19)
  - "The Net of Heaven,", n.d. (Folder 4: 20)
  - "On 100% Americans,", n.d. (Folder 4: 21)
  - "Pervoe razocharovanie," Blagoveschenskoe utro, n.d. (Folder 4: 22)
    Printed copy
  - "Russian Refugees,", n.d. (Folder 4: 23)
  - "Sea Cliff House,", n.d. (Folder 4: 24)
  - "Short Biography of Joseph Sigall,", n.d. (Folder 4: 25)
  - "Soldiers of Fortune,", n.d. (Folder 4: 26)
  - "Taxi Home,", n.d. (Folder 4: 27)
  - "Third Emigration,", n.d. (Folder 4: 28)
  - "Wey,", n.d. (Folder 4: 29)
  - "Where Are You Now?", n.d. (Folder 4: 30)
  - "Ideinaia sviaz' mezhdu liricheskimi i eticheskimi proizvedeniami Lermontova," school essay, 1913. (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - "Voiny v iubke," Blagoveschenskoe utro, 1915. (Folder 5: 2)
  - Article written for the Tokyo daily newspaper Hochi Shinbun, 1920. (Folder 5: 3)
    Printed copy. In Japanese
  - "Peasant and Bolshevik in Soviet Russia,", 1920. (Folder 5: 4)
  - "Sud'ba russkikh zhenshchin,", 1921. (Folder 5: 5)
  - "Iaponskiia poemy," Russkii golos, Harbin, 1921 April 20 (Folder 5: 6)
  - "Mezhdunarodnyi s'iezd advokatov v Pekine," Russkii golos, Harbin, 1921 October 28. (Folder 5: 7)
  - Article about Aleksandr Nikolaevich Alekseevskii, 1922. (Folder 5: 8)
  - "Theater Usherette Tells of Work: Women Most Finicky Patrons," San Francisco Examiner, 1923 March 25. (Folder 5: 9)
    Printed copy. Includes background material and review of the article
  - "'God's Own Country' Pleases Nadia; But Let Her Tell It," San Francisco Examiner, 1923 April 1. (Folder 5: 10)
  - "Mystery Is Better Than Peroxide When You're Looking for a Job," San Francisco Examiner, 1923 April 22. (Folder 5: 11)
  - "Hungry for Knowledge, Young Russians Come Here to Study," San Francisco Examiner, 1923 May 6. (Folder 5: 12)
  - "Is She Blonde, Brunette, Married or Coquette? Perfume Depends on It," San Francisco Examiner, 1923 May 20. (Folder 5: 13)
  - "200,000 Russians in Harbin Face Helplessness Under Chinese Rule," San Francisco Examiner, 1923 June 3. (Folder 5: 14)
  - "Park Tea Garden Awakens Memory of Holy Dance of Japanese Fishermen," San Francisco Examiner, 1923 June 24. (Folder 5: 15)
  - "Enoshima, Golden-Gray of Legend and Rare Romance, Swallowed by the Sea," San Francisco Examiner, 1923 September 8. (Folder 5: 16)
  - "Paris Creates, America Adapts Styles, But Yankee Inspiration Comes First," San Francisco Examiner, 1923 September 30. (Folder 5: 17)
  - "Rasputin's Pyre is Russia's Revenge: Man Who Dominated Empress Incinerated," San Francisco Examiner, 1923 October 7. (Folder 5: 18)
  - "Russia Puts Export Tax on Art Coming to America: Thousand Pictures Accompanied by Famous Artists to Be Exhibited and Sold in U.S. While Soviet Will Garner Share in Receipts," San Francisco Examiner, 1924 February 10. (Folder 5: 19)
  - "300,000 White Russians Under Yellow Rule in Harbin: With Threatened Seizure of Chinese Railroad by Soviets, Plight of Expatriate Is Complicated; Now Amenable to Laws They Cannot Read, Without a Country," San Francisco Examiner, 1924 April 6. (Folder 5: 20)
  - "Refugee Russian Writers Find Fame in Paris: Poet Here Tells Great Success of Authors in French Capital, Where 400,000 of Their Countrymen Live; Books are Being Translated Into French," San Francisco Examiner, 1924 November 9. (Folder 5: 21)
  - "Russkie genii ikonopisi," Den' russkoi kul'tury, San Francisco, 1926. (Folder 5: 22)
  - "Famed Exiles from Russia Toil for Food," San Francisco Examiner, 1928 March 30. (Folder 5: 23)
  - "An Ice Age May Blanket World Again and Astronomers Will Forecast It: Old Puzzle of Glaciers Solved" (Alaska's proof of an inter-glacial forest period), San Francisco Examiner, 1928 April 8. (Folder 5: 24)
  - "Leo Tolstoy's Birth Feted," San Francisco Examiner, 1928 May 4. (Folder 5: 25)
  - Russian refugee stories, 1929 March. (Folder 5: 26)
  - Notes regarding a reference book listing Russian writers, publications and libraries in the New World, 1929 April. (Folder 5: 27)
  - "Spusk russkago flaga na Aliaske," Novaia zaria, San Francisco, 1929 May 4. (Folder 5: 28)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - Review of Barrett Willoughby's novel The Trail Eater, San Francisco Examiner, 1929 June. (Folder 5: 29)
  - Story of the former admiral of the imperial Russian navy Eugene Klupfell, 1929 November. (Folder 5: 30)
  - "Ser'gi mistera Chena," Novaia zaria, San Francisco, 1930 January 1. (Folder 5: 31)
  - "Old Sitka's Saved," San Francisco Examiner, 1930 March 30. (Folder 5: 32)
  - "V staroi Sitkhe," Novaia zaria, San Francisco, 1930 April 20. (Folder 5: 33)
  - "How Russians Colonized Wrangel Island After Driving American Fur Hunters Off: Story Told for First Time by Captain of Soviet Ship" (Civilization's outpost claimed by Russia), San Francisco Examiner, 1930 May 4. (Folder 5: 34)
  - Story of visit with Charmian London, 1930 October. (Folder 5: 35)
    Typescripts in English and Russian
  - "Russian Refugees,", 1931-1941. (Folder 5: 36-38)
    Includes very early notes on Russian refugees adapting themselves to American life in San Francisco, also used later as background material for writing. Typescript
  - "V lunnoi doline," Rubezh, Harbin, Manchuria, China, 1931 March. (Folder 5: 39)
    Typescript and printed copy. Includes review in San Francisco Examiner
  - "Out of the Past," San Francisco Examiner, 1931 October 24. (Folder 5: 40)
  - Story about flood in Harbin, 1932 September 10. (Folder 5: 41)
  - "Russian Revolution ߝ Accounts of Eyewitnesses,", 1932 November 3. (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Includes correspondence with H. H. Fisher. Typescript
  - "Dr. Sadikoff-Goldman,", 1933. (Folder 6: 2)
  - "Halt"
    - First version, n.d. (Folder 6: 3)
    - Second version, 1929. (Folder 6: 4)
    - Third version, 1933. (Folder 6: 5)
  - "Trideviatoe tsarstvo," Novaia zaria, 1933 April 15. (Folder 6: 6)
    Also published in Kaliforniiskii al'manakh, San Francisco, 1934. Printed copies
  - "Naturalization,", 1933 August 25. (Folder 6: 7)
  - "My Old Town Was Blagoveschensk," Los Angeles Times Sunday Magazine, 1933 September 24. (Folder 6: 8)
  - "Roman velikogo kniazia," Novaia zaria, 1933 December 23-27. (Folder 6: 9)
  - "Father Andrew Kashevaroff on Flying Visit Here, Tells of Struggle to Save His Churches from Seizure by Moscow Government,", 1934 (?). (Folder 6: 10)
  - "Professors,", 1934 (?). (Folder 6: 11)
  - "Rezanov's Library," preliminary notes, 1934.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - "Short History of the Rezanov Library,", 1934.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - "Russia,", 1934 February 5. (Folder 6: 12)
  - "Voskresenie Germanii," translated from German, 1934 March 20. (Folder 6: 13)
  - "The Melting Pot Boils," The Christian Science Monitor, 1934 May 28. (Folder 6: 14)
  - "Emigrés,", 1934 June. (Folder 6: 15)
  - "Rare Rezanov Russian Books Found in San Francisco," San Francisco Chronicle, 1934 June 10.; See Subject File/ Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
    Printed copy.
  - "Torao Gives All for Job in Manchukuo," San Francisco Chronicle, 1934 June 10. (Folder 6: 16)
  - "Russian Exiles Organize into Many Factions," San Francisco Chronicle, 1934 June 24. (Folder 6: 17)
  - "Russian Ex-Officers Enemies Now in Chaco," San Francisco Chronicle, 1934 August 18.; See also Subject File/Russia ߝ Revolution - White officers and soldiers in foreign armies. (Folder 6: 18)
  - "Zhena komendanta forta Ross," Dolg chesti, 1934 October. (Folder 6: 19)
  - "Coincidence,", 1935. (Folder 6: 20)
  - "The Emerald,", 1935 July 27. (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "Russkii Kolumb,", 1935 December 6. (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Russian Writers in California,", 1935 December 8. (Folder 7: 3)
  - "Box Car to Siberia,", 1936 January 31. (Folder 7: 4)
  - "Soldiers of Fortune,", 1936 May 1. (Folder 7: 5)
  - Alaska writings, 1937-1944. (Folder 7: 6)
    Typescripts
  - "How Much Is a Rouble Worth?", 1937 April 26. (Folder 7: 7)
  - "O chem govoriat," Russkie novosti San Frantsisco, 1937 May - September. (Folder 7: 8)
  - "Comrades Together,", 1938. (Folder 7: 9)
  - "Journey Through Time" (A loose sort of autobiography), 1940. (Folder 7: 10)
  - "V starinu zhivali dedy," Russkie novosti, 1941 April 18. (Folder 7: 11)
  - "Black Out the Moon,", 1941 September 9. (Folder 7: 12)
  - "Dostan'te interv'iu," Russkaia zhizn', 1941 December 24. (Folder 7: 13)
  - "Political Refugees and Their Rehabilitation," 1944 April 17. Paper submitted as a final test for an UNRRA course offered by the University of California extension division. (Folder 7: 14)